<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors | CORE Lab</title>
    <link>/authors/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Authors</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/corelogo-big.png</url>
      <title>Authors</title>
      <link>/authors/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Department of Defense Analysis is home to the CORE (Common Operational Research Environment) Lab. CORE was established at the Naval Postgraduate School (NPS) in 2007 with the mission to support U.S. and International field operatives in the analytical craft of integrating geospatial, cultural, relational, and temporal data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is our practioner&#39;s page, which contains a curated set of resources that we have developed for practioners and field operators. Our organizational site with further information on who we are can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://my.nps.edu/web/core&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robert Ford</title>
      <link>/authors/robert-ford/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/authors/robert-ford/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/authors/sean-everton/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/authors/sean-everton/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sean Everton is an Assistant Professor in the Department of Defense Analysis and the Co-Director of the CORE Lab at the Naval Postgraduate School (NPS). Prior to joining NPS in 2007 he served as an adjunct professor at both Santa Clara University and Stanford University. Professor Everton earned his MA and PhD in Sociology at Stanford University (2007) and wrote his doctoral thesis on causes and consequences of status on the economic performance of venture capital firms. He has published in the areas of social network analysis, sociology of religion, economic sociology, and political sociology and currently specializes in the use of social network analysis to track and disrupt dark networks (e.g., criminal and terrorist networks). His monograph on using social network analysis for the crafting of strategies for the disruption of dark networks was published by Cambridge University Press in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
